

# Rafael Cabral

□+351 939074882 | ☑ rafael.medeiros.cabral@gmail.com | 匝 rafael-medeiros-cabral

### Summary.

As a statistics researcher, I specialize in applied and computational statistics. My research revolves around building more robust and computationally efficient modelling frameworks for spatial and temporal data. I have worked with Gaussian and non-Gaussian processes, model criticism and robustness, and approximate inference with MCMC, INLA, and variational inference. I also did internships in the industry in data science, deep neural networks, and image segmentation. My website is rafaelcabral96.github.io.

### Education

**Ph.D. in Statistics**KAUST

Saudi Arabia
2020 - 2023

- Thesis entitled Criticism and robustification of latent Gaussian models.
- Supervised by Profs. Håvard Rue and David Bolin

#### M.Sc. in Applied Mathematics

INSTITUTO SUPERIOR TÉCNICO - UNIVERSITY OF LISBON

Lisbon, Portugal 2017 - 2019

- Thesis entitled Space-time trends and dependence of wind extremes in north-western Germany.
- Top degree in Portugal: the lowest entry grade is 18.35/20.

#### **B.Sc. in Engineering Physics**

Instituto Superior Técnico - University of Lisbon

• Top degree in Portugal: the lowest entry grade is 18.9/20.

Lisbon, Portugal 2014 - 2017

# Awards

2022	Al-Kindi Statistics Research Student Award, a research award for top Statistics Ph.D. students at KAUST	Saudi Arabia
2022	McKinsey & Company, Forward program	Saudi Arabia
2022	Dean's list award, during Ph.D. at KAUST	Saudi Arabia
2020-2022 Ph.D. progress rated as Outstanding (A+), by the KAUST evaluation committee		Saudi Arabia
2019	Research fellowship grant, for the development of research work in extreme value theory (FCT-BL299/2018)	Portugal
2019	Diploma of academic merit, for great performance in the M.Sc. in Applied Mathematics	Portugal
2017	Diploma of academic merit, for great performance in the B.Sc. in Engineering Physics	Portugal
2013	Asteroid Discovery Award, International Astronomical Search Collaboration. Confirmed asteroid by the	Portugal
	Minor Planet Center of the University of Harvard with name 2013 EZ7	

### **Publications**

#### Fitting latent non-Gaussian models using variational Bayes and Laplace approximations

R. Cabral, D. Bolin, and H. Rue, arXiv (PREPRINT)

2022

- Paper: arxiv.org/abs/2211.11050
- R package: github.com/rafaelcabral96/ngvb/

#### Controlling the flexibility of non-Gaussian processes through shrinkage priors

R. CABRAL, D. BOLIN, AND H. RUE, Bayesian Analysis

2022

- Paper: doi.org/10.1214/22-BA1342
- Github: github.com/stan-dev/connect22-space-time

#### Space-time trends and dependence of precipitation extremes in north-western Germany

R. Cabral, A. Ferreira, and P. Friederichs, *Environmetrics* 

2019

• Paper: doi.org/10.1002/env.2605

A price model with finitely many agents

A. Alharbi, T. Barkaryan, R. Cabral, et al., Bulletin of the Portuguese Mathematical Society

2019

Paper: hdl.handle.net/10754/662310

**Professional Experience** 

#### Internship on Optimization KAUST

Saudi Arabia 2019

Implemented and improved a particle-swarm optimization algorithm

- Application to non-convex function optimization and machine learning problems.
- Python (Numpy and Tensorflow).

**Data Science Internship** 

ODYSAL

Lisbon, Portugal

2018

- Startup developing Docdigitizer, a product that automatically extracts information from documents using machine learning.
- Data processing tasks using Python.
- Designed real-time analytics dashboards to understand user behavior and product performance.

#### **Deep Learning Internship**

Lisbon, Portugal

2018

HOSPITAL DA LUZ LEARNING HEALTH

- Won the IST Enterprise Challenge competition on how AI can aid the medical industry.
- Applied deep learning algorithms to segment 3D medical images automatically.
- Convolutional neural networks in Python (Keras and Tensorflow).

# **Data Science Spring Program** BNP PARIBAS

Lisbon, Portugal

2018

• Worked with Alteryx for data processing and Tableau for data visualization.

# Leadership experience\_

Student AmbassadorSaudi ArabiaKAUST2021-2023

- Represented the CEMSE division and aided in its recruitment efforts.
- Promoted the Statistics program abroad.

# Teaching assistant on the stochastic processes course KAUST

Saudi Arabia 2020-2022

- Mandatory course in M.Sc./Ph.D. in Statistics and Electrical Engineering with 45 attending students.
- Designed course projects, weekly homeworks and graded exams and projects.
- Delivered weekly lectures where I solved the homework live and answered students' questions.

# Attended conferences and workshops\_

### StanConnect 2022: Stan Through Space and Time

Online

- Speaker: Robust non-Gaussian models and how to fit them in Stan.
- github.com/stan-dev/connect22-space-time

#### Summer school: Statistics for Point Patterns in Space and Beyond AALBORG UNIVERSITY

Aalborg, Denmark

2022

2022

• Attended classes given by Professors Jesper Møller and Rasmus Waagepetersen.

# 2022 ISBA world meeting International Society for Bayesian Analysis

Montreal, Canada

2022

Poster: Controlling the flexibility of non-Gaussian processes through shrinkage priors

## Referrals.

Håvard Rue Professor, Statistics haavard.rue@kaust.edu.sa KAUST, Saudi Arabia David Bolin

Associate Professor, Statistics david.bolin@kaust.edu.sa KAUST, Saudi Arabia